<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Virginia. A sermon preached at White-Chappel, in the presence of many, honourable and worshipfull, the aduenturers and planters for Virginia. 25. April. 1609 Published for the benefit and vse of the colony, planted, and to bee planted there, and for the aduancement of their Christian purpose. By William Symonds, preahcer at Saint Sauiors in Southwarke..</title>
            <author>Symonds, William, 1556-1616?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846695</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 726:12, 2340:8b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Virginia. A sermon preached at White-Chappel, in the presence of many, honourable and worshipfull, the aduenturers and planters for Virginia. 25. April. 1609 Published for the benefit and vse of the colony, planted, and to bee planted there, and for the aduancement of their Christian purpose. By William Symonds, preahcer at Saint Sauiors in Southwarke..</title>
                  <author>Symonds, William, 1556-1616?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Windet, for Eleazar Edgar, and William Welby, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Windmill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank except for marginal rules.</note>
                  <note>The item at reel 2340:8b is second in a group ten items bound and filmed together.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in: New York Public Library (reel 726:12) and Boston Public Library (reel 2340:8b).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XII, 1-3 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Colonies --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11682:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGINIA.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT WHITE-CHAPPEL, IN THE preſence of many, Honourable and Worſhipfull, the Aduenturers and Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for VIRGINIA. 25. <hi>April.</hi> 1609. PVBLISHED FOR THE BENEFIT AND VSE OF THE COLONY, PLANTED, And to bee Planted there, and for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of their CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAN Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SYMONDS, Preacher at Saint SAVIORS <hi>in Southwarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IVDE. 22. 23.</bibl>
               <p>Haue compaſſion of ſome, in putting of difference:</p>
               <p>And other ſaue with feare, pulling them out of the fire.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by I. WINDET, for ELEAZAR EDGAR, and <hi>William Welby,</hi> and are to be ſold in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard at the Signe of the Windmill. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11682:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11682:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND WORTHIE ADVANCERS OF THE STANDART of CHRIST, among the GENTILES, the Aduenturers for the Plantation of VIRGINIA, <hi>W. S.</hi> prayeth that Nations may bleſſe them, and be bleſſed by them.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Noble and worthy,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCH as doe prayſe the worthies, do cloth them with the robes of others that haue gone before them in vertues of like nature. A thing which I cannot doe of your Plantation, ſeeing neither Teſtament (that I can find) dooth afford vs a Parallell in men of like quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. That great, and golden SEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENCE, <hi>The ſeede of the woman, ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 3. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11682:3"/> 
               <hi>breake the Serpents head,</hi> (the onely ſubiect of all ages) with a part of the wiſedome that is folded therin, hitherto hath beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified the world with admirable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant varieties; more rich and delightfull then all the ornaments of Princes palaces, or the Curtaines of <hi>Salomon.</hi> Here may we ſee the Flood, the burning of Sodom; the drown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of <hi>Pharoh:</hi> the ſubduing of the Cananites by <hi>Dauid</hi> and his ſonnes; the breaking of Monarchies into chaffe: the<note place="margin">Dan. 2. 35.</note> ſurpriſing &amp; conquering of great Nations,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6. 17.</note> by Fiſher-men, <hi>with the ſword of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> the ſtamping of the Dragon (the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Empire) into pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es by <hi>Conſtantine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Constantini.</note> the deſolation, and nakedneſſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, now readie to be caſt into the fire. Manifeſt demonſtrations of the Serpents bruiſed head. But here is not all. Theſe things were done in a corner, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that which is in hand, and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be accompliſhed at the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Long ſince the Goſpell <hi>of Christ did ride forth conquering that hee might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 6. &amp;. 19.</note> And NOW, <hi>the hoſtes that are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:11682:3"/> doe follow him on white horſes. Now the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 52. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Lord hath made bare his holy arme, in the ſight</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 19. 12.</note> 
               <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Gentiles; and all the ends of the earth ſhall ſee the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our God.</hi> NOW many Mighty Kings haue ſet their Crownes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of Chriſt. The valiant ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſaith, <hi>The ſhields of the world belong to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 47. 9.</note> 
               <hi>God.</hi> The true Nobilitie, haue vpon their horſe bridles, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi> And<note place="margin">Zach. 14. 20.</note> now the wiſe and induſtrious Merchant, doth hold the riches of the Gentiles too baſe a fraight for his ſhippes. He tradeth<note place="margin">Iſai. 60. 9.</note> for <hi>his</hi> wiſedome, that ſaid: <hi>Surely the Iſles wait for me</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and the ſhippes of the Ocean most eſpecially:</hi> namely to carry the Goſpell abroad. The people in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, like ſtronge thundrings, doe ſay <hi>Hallelu-iah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And who is wanting in this<note place="margin">Reuel. 19. 6.</note> bleſſed expedition? Surely, not any tribe, <hi>Prayſe ye the Lord, — for the people that offered</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>themſelues ſo willingly.</hi> For who can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelfe from concurrence in ſo good an action: eſpecially, when he ſhall but read, or heare, that one ſentence which <hi>Deborah</hi> did ſing: <hi>Curſe ye</hi> Meroz, <hi>ſayd the
<pb facs="tcp:11682:4"/> Angell of the Lord curſe the inhabitants therof:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5. 23.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they came not forth to helpe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This land, was of old time, offered to our Kings. Our late Soueraigne Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> (whoſe ſtorie hath no peere among Princes of her ſexe) being a pure Virgin, found it, ſet foot in it, and called it <hi>Virginia.</hi> Our moſt ſacred Soueraigne, in whom is the ſpirit of his great Anceſtor, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſtantin t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e pacifier of the world, and planter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtantin.</note> 
               <hi>in places moſt remote,</hi> deſireth to preſent this land a pure Virgine to Chriſt. Such as doe mannage the expedition, are carefull to carry thither no Traitors, nor Papiſts that depend on the Great <hi>VVhore. Lord fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh this good worke thou haſt begun;</hi> and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this land, a pure Virgine to thy kingly ſonne Chriſt Ieſus; ſo ſhall thy name bee magnified: and we ſhall haue a Virgin or Maiden Britaine, a comfortable addition to our Great Britaine.</p>
            <p>And now Right Worthy, if any aske an account of my vocation, to write and Preach thus much; I anſwere: that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I could not ſatisfie their requeſt
<pb facs="tcp:11682:4"/> that would haue me goe; yet I could not omit to ſhewe my zeale to the glory of God. If they aske account of my Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I anſwere, your vertue hath exacted it. If any man liſt to be curious, or conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, wee haue no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God. Hold on your bleſſed courſe, and you ſhall receiue bleſsings of Chriſt. <hi>Bleſsed bee the Lord God; euen the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 72. 18. 19.</note> 
               <hi>God of Iſraell, which onely worketh great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and hath put theſe bleſſed thoughts into your Chriſtian hearts, <hi>And bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be his glorious name for euer, and let all the earth be filled with his glory, Amen, Amen. </hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fours moſt heartily affected in the cauſe of Virginia, WILLIAM SIMONDS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11682:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11682:5"/>
            <head>VIRGINEA BRITANNIA. <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT WHITE CHAPPELL, IN THE preſence of many the Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and Planters for VIRGINIA.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GENESIS 12. 1. 2. 3.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>For the Lord had ſaid vnto Abram, Get thee out of thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and from thy kindred, and from thy fathers houſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land that I will ſhew thee.</p>
                  <p>And I will make of thee a great nation, and will bleſſe thee, and make thy name great, and thou ſhalt be a bleſsing.</p>
                  <p>I will bleſſe them alſo that bleſſe thee, and curſe them that curſe thee, and in thee ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Booke of Geneſis contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſtory of the Creation and Plantation of heauen and earth, with conuenient inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. The heauen hath An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the skie ſtarres, the aire foules, the water fiſhes, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11682:6"/> earth (furniſhed with plants and hearbes, and beaſts) was prouided for man a while to inhabite, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was to be receiued into glory, <hi>like vnto the Angels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 22. 30.</note> Hereupon the Lord (who by his great decree, ſet downe by his whole Trinitie, had determined that man ſhould rule among the creatures) did make man, both male and female, <hi>After his owne image,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4. 4.</note> that is, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> and gaue them this bleſſing, <hi>Bring forth fruit and multiplie, and fill the earth, and ſubdue</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. 28.</note> 
               <hi>it, &amp;c.</hi> And howſoeuer this precept might ſeeme to finde interruption by the ſinne of man, that had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred the curſe <hi>to die the death:</hi> yet we ſee that God<note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17 &amp; 3. 3. Iſai. 45. 23. Gen. 9. 1, 2.</note> would not, for any thing, alter <hi>his oath and word, that was gone out of his mouth;</hi> for vnto <hi>Noah</hi> hee reuiued this precept after the flood.</p>
            <p>But as all the commandements of God doe finde rebellion againſt them: ſo hath this moſt ſpecially; inſomuch that the whole earth conſpired to make open inſurrection againſt it, by <hi>building of a Citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and Towne,</hi> the better to continue together. For the ſubduing of which rebellion, <hi>The Lord came downe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11. 7</note> 
               <hi>and confounded their languages, and ſcattered them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad:</hi> Not onely to the ouerthrow of their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who ſought <hi>a great name;</hi> but alſo to depriue them of his ſpirituall grace of ſaluation, one being not able to vnderſtand the other: And ſo of the ſonnes of <hi>Noah, were the Nations diuided after the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 32.</note> 
               <hi>flood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among whome the bleſſed line of <hi>Shem</hi> is not<note place="margin">Gen 11. 10.</note> onely plentifully remembred; but alſo commended, as obedient vnto that firſt and great Law of God:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11682:6"/> For <hi>Terah, the father of Abram,</hi> with his family, are reported to be found in a Land not theirs, that they might fill the earth.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why <hi>Terah,</hi> and his family remoued,<note place="margin">The context.</note> is recorded in theſe three verſes; and, in a word, is the calling of <hi>Abram</hi> by the Lord to remooue. In the ſtorie whereof, are theſe two points: Firſt the the vocation of <hi>Abram,</hi> in theſe three verſes, and then his obedience vnto this heauenly calling, in the fourth verſe. His vocation hath firſt the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord, and then the reaſons and argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, by which God doeth induce him thereunto. The commandement is to take a iourney; in which we muſt conſider the places from whence, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Goe out of</note> he was to goe. The place from whence, is not deſcribed Coſmographically, but Morally, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning three important reaſons, in all good ſort, to reſt him where hee was. The firſt is his <hi>Countrey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thy Country.</note> which was pleaſant, and fruitfull: The ſecond his kindred, which was holy and bleſſed: The third, <hi>his fathers houſe,</hi> which was louing and rich. Hence muſt hee goe, and leaue them all behind, if they would not goe with him. The place whither hee muſt goe is alſo very generally noted out: Namely, the place <hi>which God would ſhew him:</hi> a place vtterly<note place="margin">To the place which I ſhall ſhew thee.</note> vnknowen <hi>vnto him,</hi> ſo that from thence he had no argument, to quicken him to that voyage.</p>
            <p>The arguments which the Lord doth vſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade<note place="margin">Arguments from promiſes.</note> 
               <hi>Abram,</hi> to this iourney are all taken from the promiſes of God; a ſtronger reaſon then the very ſweetneſſe of Paradiſe could be vnto a faithful man.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11682:7"/> Theſe promiſes doe partly concerne <hi>Abram</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, partly thoſe among whom he ſhall liue. For himſelfe the Lord doeth promiſe foure things: Firſt tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, whereas himſelfe was childleſſe, <hi>He w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld make</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. A great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>of him a great nation.</hi> A thing which the builders of Babel drifted but were diſappointed of by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">2. Bleſſe thee.</note> of God. The ſecond promiſe is, that <hi>God will bleſse him,</hi> by giuing him the good things of this preſent world, and that which is to come: A thing which the builders of Babel loſt, by tranſgreſſing Gods commandement of repleniſhing the earth.<note place="margin">3. A great name.</note> The third thing is, that the Lord <hi>will make him a great name,</hi> with much honour, and good report; which the confounded builders of Babel ſought, and miſſed, becauſe of their ſinne. The fourth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe<note place="margin">4. A bleſſing.</note> is, that he ſhall be <hi>a bleſsing:</hi> That is, ſuch a one as men ſhall be the better where hee commeth; and ſo thinke themſelues, ſeeing that through him, as through a golden Pipe, the Lord will beſtow his bleſſings vpon his family, and others among whom he liueth.</p>
            <p>The arguments that concerne other men, are of two ſorts; the one is their Temporall eſtate; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Spirituall. Concerning the Temporall eſtate of thoſe amongſt whom hee liueth, God will diſpoſe of, as they diſpoſe themſelues towards <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bram:</hi> For the Lord <hi>will bleſſe them,</hi> and cauſe them<note place="margin">1. Bleſſe them that bleſſe thee.</note> to proſper, that ſeeke the <hi>bleſsing</hi> and proſperitie of <hi>Abram.</hi> And againe, if they ſtand otherwiſe affected towards <hi>Abram,</hi> then will the Lord alſo ſet his face<note place="margin">2. Curſe them that curſe thee.</note> againſt them, in theſe words: <hi>And I will curſe them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11682:7"/> that curſe thee:</hi> So that nothing they haue ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, vntill they be gracious and fauorable to <hi>Abram.</hi> That which concerneth their Spirituall eſtate, is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede an argument to a faithfull man, ſtronger then chaines of Adamant; Namely, that by this meanes, the people all abroad ſhall receiue the grace of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.<note place="margin">3. All Nations bleſſed.</note> The thing he promiſeth is ſaluation by the Goſpel, in this word, <hi>I will bleſſe.</hi> The meanes, is <hi>Abram</hi> and his ſeede IESVS CHRIST: in theſe words <hi>in thee.</hi> The perſons, to receiue benefit by him, are infinite; euen all the families of <hi>Noah,</hi> by whom the nations of all <hi>the earth were diuided;</hi> In theſe words, <hi>And in thee, ſhall all the families of the earth bee bleſſed.</hi> This is the ſenſe of theſe three ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: In which are very many excellent things to bee obſerued, but we will onely inſiſt vpon thoſe, which are proper to our occaſion, &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DOCTRINES.</head>
               <note place="margin">jo. Abraham cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Lord called Abraham to goe into another Countrey.</hi> There is no doubt, but that there is a double manner of calling; the one ordinary, by ſome knowne precept of the word of God: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Mat 1. 20. Num. 12. 6.</note> extraordinary when as by dreame, or by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, God requireth any duetie to be done. Now if it be demaunded how <hi>Abraham</hi> was called, to goe into another Countrey: the anſwere is, both ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily and extraordinarily. It was a knowne rule of the word of God, concluded, and pronounced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Creation, and often repeated afterwards,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11682:8"/> that man ſhould ſpread abroad, &amp;c. <hi>and inhabite the earth, and fill it.</hi> Hitherto belongeth that, which God ſaid; <hi>Let vs make man in our image, and let them rule ouer the Fiſh of the Sea, and ouer the Fowles of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Heauen, and ouer the Beaſtes, and ouer</hi> ALL <hi>the earth.</hi> Then muſt he repleniſh the earth, elſe can hee not rule ouer ALL. To the ſame effect is that ſpoken of <hi>Adam,</hi> after his fall, that <hi>God ſent him forth of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Garden of Eden to till the earth:</hi> ſo that the fall of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> did not, in the leaſt thing, cauſe the Lord to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his firſt decree. So to <hi>Noah</hi> after the flood;<note place="margin">Gen. 9. 2, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Bring forth fruite, and multiply, grow plentifully in the earth, and encreaſe therein, and repleniſh the earth.</hi> By all this it doth appeare, that God did call <hi>Abraham</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, by a general Vocation. But when he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a certaine place, and vnder certaine conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is alſo plaine, that withall, he had a ſpecial and extraordinary calling, either by dreame or by viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by ſome ſuch extraordinary meane, which (til the Canon of the Scripture came fully in) was to be obeyed as the written word of God. Yet ſtill wee muſt remember that this ſpeciall calling was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the generall law of repleniſhing the earth. For although God called him to one land; yet to vpholde the generall rule, God often laide a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon him to ſpread further: for in this Chapter, by reaſon of a famine, hee was conſtreined to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne<note place="margin">Gen 12. 10. &amp;c</note> in Egipt: God did alſo tell him before hand, <hi>that his ſeede ſhould be a ſtranger, in a land that is not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>theirs, foure hundred yeares.</hi> It is true, that the Iewes did holde themſelues ſo confined to their owne
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11682:8"/> land, that they were as loth to forgoe their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as from the Sacrament of their ſaluation: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>King. 21. 3.</hi>
                  </note> be <hi>Naboth,</hi> that anſwered the King; <hi>The Lord keepe me from giuing the inheritance of my fathers vnto thee.</hi> And yet, when God would haue it ſo, as when there was famine, <hi>Elimelech</hi> and his Familie<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. 1. 1. 2.</note> goe to ſoiourne among the Gentiles. In time of warre <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke his father and mother, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Sam.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3.</note> them to ſoiourne with the King of Moab. And<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5.</note> when as we reade that there <hi>were dwelling at Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Iewes of euery nation vnder heauen;</hi> it is plaine, that the Iewes did ſpread abroad, not onely to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne for a time, and then to come againe; but to<note place="margin">Act. 22. 3.</note> inhabite and repleniſh the whole earth. <hi>Paul</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Iew, borne in Cilicia, euen in a Romane Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie.</p>
               <p>The reaſon why God will haue his to fill the<note place="margin">1. Reaſon. To knowe Gods works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> earth is, becauſe the Lord would haue his workes to be knowne. Now in diuers Countries God hath his diuers workes, of hearbes, and trees, and beaſtes, and fiſhes, and fowles, and ſerpents, &amp;c. which (if the people of God come not there) cannot praiſe the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> Creator. When <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>All thy workes praiſe thee, O God, and thy Saints bleſſe thee; they ſhew the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy kingdome, and ſpeake of thy power:</hi> the impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is manifeſt, that his Saints muſt be witneſſes of all his workes, in all Climates; for elſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<note place="margin">II.</note> bleſſe him in all his workes. Another reaſon is,<note place="margin">Spreading of knowledge.</note> that one that hath the knowledge of the feare of God, ſhould communicate it to others: Hereupon<note place="margin">Pſal. 67. 1. 2.</note> is it that <hi>Dauid</hi> doeth teach vs to pray thus; <hi>Haue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11682:9"/> mercie on vs Lord, and bleſſe vs, and cauſe thy face to ſhine among vs, Selah.</hi> Marke this, that he biddeth vs pray, <hi>God be mercifull vnto vs;</hi> The meanes how, is this: <hi>That they may know thy way vpon earth, and thy ſauing health among all nations;</hi> whereby he doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that God hath with-held ſome mercy from vs, til all nations haue the meanes of ſaluation. This was<note place="margin">Exod, 11. 9.</note> a cauſe why God ſent <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſterity into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, that by their meanes <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe heart was bigge, and would not acknowledge God, might be conſtrained to fall down, and ſay, <hi>I haue ſinned againſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 10. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord.</hi> The cauſe alſo of the captiuity of the Iewes in Babilon, in the ſecrete prouidence of God, was, that the Monarkes of the world, who thought<note place="margin">Dan. 4. 20. 21. 17. 29.</note> there was no God could come neere them in greatnes, might be as beaſtes before God, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that it is God, that giueth Kingdomes to whom he will. And when the Lord had cauſed his people to returne, and to build their Citie and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; yet would not God fore-ſlowe the inforcing of his precept, <hi>Fill the earth.</hi> For whereas, by reaſon of his promiſe, he could not ſend the people abroad till Chriſt came, to make his glory knowne, he brought vpon them <hi>Gog and Magog,</hi> with their numberſome<note place="margin">Ezek. 38. 16. 23</note> Armies: The reaſon is, that <hi>the Heathen may knowe the Lord: I wil be magnified, and ſanctified, and knowne in the eyes of many Nations.</hi> Then here muſt wee know, that what inducement <hi>Abraham</hi> had, to goe<note place="margin">VSE. I.</note> out of his Countrey, by a generall calling, the ſame doth binde all his ſonnes, according to the faith, to goe likewiſe abroad, when God doth not otherwiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11682:9"/> call them to ſome ſpeciall affaires: How euer, ſtill they muſt haue a longing, and a liking to ſpread the Goſpel abroad. And that this point may be eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conuicted vnto vs, Chriſt our Sauiour hath, according to his infinite wiſedome, reuiued the olde law, of filling the earth, in a moſt excellent manner: <hi>Goe teach</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all nations, and baptize them in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 28. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>name of the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Gaue hee this Commaundement to his Apoſtles onely? haue not alſo the labours of godly Preachers, which they haue ſpread ouer the face of the whole earth, beene beſtowed by the power of this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And though the words, as they lie, doe binde the Miniſters of the Word, to endeuour the propa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpell, with all their power; yet not onely them: For we reade, that poore Tent-makers and others, haue done much good in ſpreading the<note place="margin">Acts 18. 3. 26.</note> Goſpell, according to their vocations: they alſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying<note place="margin">II.</note> thus much of Chriſts precept. Neither can there be any doubt, but that the Lord that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Abraham</hi> into another Countrey, doeth alſo by the ſame holy hand, call you to goe and carry the Goſpell to a Nation that neuer heard of Chriſt. The Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> ſpeaking of the daies of the Goſpell, doth ſhew, that it is a good Vocation for men to goe abroad, when the number of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God doe exceede; his wordes are theſe: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of hoſtes, my cities ſhall yet be broken with plenty, the Lord ſhall yet comfort Zion.</hi> Vnto<note place="margin">Zach. 1. 17.</note> whom agreeth the Prophet <hi>Iſatah: The children of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 49. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>thy barrenneſſe ſhall ſay againe, in thine eares, the place
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11682:10"/> is too ſtrait for me, giue me place, that I may dwell.</hi> Wherefore ſeeing that, thankes be to God, we are thronged with multitude; the Lord of hoſtes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath giuen vs the calling of his children to<note place="margin">Obiection. Not to enter other Princes Territories.</note> ſeeke for roome, and place to dwell in. And heere might we haue proceeded to the next point, were it not for one ſcruple, which ſome, that thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be very wiſe, do caſt in our way; which is this in effect. The countrey, they ſay, is poſſeſſed by owners, that rule, and gouerne it in their owne right: then with what conſcience, and equitie can we offer to thruſt them, by violence, out of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances?<note place="margin">1. Anſwere. Conqueſt law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> For anſwere to this obiection: firſt it is plaine, that the obiecter ſuppoſeth it not lawfull to inuade the territories of other princes, by force of ſword. This propoſition I confeſſe I neuer was willing to examine, conſidering my vocation is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate. And if <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> the Emperour, ſaid well,<note place="margin">CARION.</note> that he merueiled euery man auoided all labors and difficulties, but onely to rule, which is the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult of all other labours; then to giue ſentence of that, which in ruling is the moſt waightie, namely, warres, which are done with the greateſt counſell, muſt needes bee a labour too heauie for a priuate mans ſhoulders. And becauſe my ſelfe am but weake eyed in ſo great a myſterie; Come foorth ye great Princes, and Monarkes, of Aſſyria, Perſia, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, Greece and Rome, with your graueſt counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and anſwere for your facts, in conquering and ſubduing nations. For your ſtories, that were wont to be read with ſingular admiration of your forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11682:10"/> your wiſedome, your magnificence, and your great iuſtice, are now araigned, and muſt bee found guiltie, that through your ſides, an action, of truer honour, then euer you attempted, may bee wounded. Your ſtrong title of the ſword, heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore magnified by Hiſtorians, Polititians, and Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, is to our obiecter, but a ſpiders web, or the hatching of a Cockatrice his egge. But whatſoeuer the reſt can ſay for their owne defence, the Lord himſelfe doth ſay thus much for <hi>Cyrus: Thus ſaith</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 45. 1. 2. 3. 4</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord vnto</hi> Cyrus, <hi>his anointed: whoſe right hand I haue holden to ſubdue nations before him: therefore will I weaken the loynes of Kings, and open the doores before him, and the gates ſhall not be ſhut: I will goe before thee, and make the crooked ſtraight: I will breake the braſen doores, and burſt the yron barres. And I will giue thee the treaſures of darkeneſſe, and the things hid in ſecret places; that thou maiſt know, that I am the Lord, which call thee by thy name, euen the God of Iſraell. For Iacob my ſeruants ſake, and Iraell mine elect, I will euen call thee by thy name, and name thee, though thou haſt not knowen me.</hi> Then who can blame <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and keepe himſelfe from blaſpheming the almightie. Nay, that which is more to be trembled at, we muſt alſo to ſummon vp, and call to the barre, the moſt holy worthies of the Scripture: and ſee if man, or God, hath any thing to be ſaid for them, why they ſhould not be condemned as iniuſt, cruell, and bloudy. <hi>O Iacob,</hi> thy bleſſed bow and ſword, with the fruit whereof thou bleſſedſt thy ſonne <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> the ſtaffe of<note place="margin">Gene. 48. 22.</note> thy gray head, and feeble knees, muſt be broken and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11682:11"/> burnt: and thou muſt bee condemned for thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull conqueſt. Worthy <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> &amp; moſt worthy <hi>Dauid,</hi> with thy cloud of worthies, who hanged vp ſo many ſhields in the houſe of God, and who ſweetly ſingeth, that <hi>God was his fortitude and buckler,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2. Ioſh.</hi> 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> muſt incurre the note of iniuſtice. <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> where is thy vertue, to ſet thy feete vpon the neckes of princes, in their owne kingdomes, and call of the meaneſt of the people to be thy partners in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie? <hi>Dauid,</hi> how vvilt thou anſwere for the blood thy ſword hath ſhed? which thou vvaſt vvont to praiſe, <hi>There is none to it.</hi> Nay thou glory of men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Sam.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> and true type of Chriſt, King <hi>Salomon,</hi> whoſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vvas like vnto the vviſedome of God: teach vs to ſay ſomevvhat in thy defence. (For one graine of thy wiſedome is of more worth then a talent of their leaden wits, that we are conſtrained to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.) Giue an account of his innocencie that ſaid vnto thee: <hi>Girde thee vvith thy ſworde vpon thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5</note> 
                  <hi>thigh, O thou moſt mightie, — Thy right hand ſhall teach thee terrible things, - The people ſhall fall vnder thee.</hi> Thy father, the ſonne of <hi>Iſhai,</hi> made a ſinfull prayer for thee (as our obiecters blaſpheme) vvhen he ſaid, thou ſhouldeſt ſo enlarge thy borders, that <hi>Thy do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minion</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſhould be from ſea to ſea, and from the riuer to the end of the land.</hi> He vvould haue thee too rigid, when he ſaith, <hi>That thine enemies ſhould licke the duſt.</hi> Sure I am perſvvaded that at the onely naming of ſo mightie Monarches, and holy conquerors, our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecters out of their modeſtie vvill vvith ſome diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction qualifie their propoſition, and ſay that it is not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11682:11"/> lavvfull, by force to inuade the Territories of other Princes, that are in quiet poſſeſſion, in ſome ſort, and in ſome caſes. I know that the diuell himſelfe, vvith all his diſtinctions, that euer he made, vvhich are recorded in ſcripture, or vvhich he left in hell, in his cabinet of <hi>Abſtruſe Studies,</hi> (locked ſafe, till hee found out the Ieſuits his truſtie ſecretaries to keepe them:) I ſay none of them all can arme a ſubiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his prince vvithout ſinne. But he that will ſet open his ſchoole in the fantaſticall ſhop of his addle imagination, (for he will be hiſſed out of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities) and take vpon him to nurture princes, as petties: telling them that they muſt not make offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue warres, if it were to gaine the whole world to Chriſt, ſhall neuer be bidders of gueſts to <hi>the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Luke 14. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>of the kings ſonne,</hi> who are required to compell them to <hi>come in.</hi> And if I might be ſo bold, I would faine aske one queſtion of theſe obiecters, that come dropping out of ſome Anabaptiſts Spicery: whether (if it be vnlawfull to conquere) the crowne ſit well on the head of our moſt ſacred ſoueraigne? (<hi>whoſe dayes be as the dayes of heauen O Lord</hi>) For by this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection they ſhew, that had they power to vntwiſt that, which in ſo many ages hath beene well ſpunne, they would write him crowneleſſe, as farre as hee hath his title from the conqueror.<note place="margin">2. No wrong to bring in the Goſpel. <hi>Matth. 7. 5.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>O but God forbid, ſaith the obiecter, that wee ſhould doe any wrong at all, no not to the diuell. The rule of Chriſt is excellent; <hi>Caſt out the beame of thine owne eye, ſo ſhalt thou ſee clearely, to caſt the mote out of thy brothers eye.</hi> If you will needs bee caſting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11682:12"/> ſtones, <hi>Let him beginne firſt, that is without ſinne.</hi> But<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 7.</note> to the point: our obiecter would not whip a child to teach him learning and vertue, for feare of doing wrong. What wrong I pray you did the Apoſtles in going about to alter the lawes of nations, euen againſt the expreſſe commandement of the princes, and to ſet vp the throne of Chriſt. If your mouth be ſo foule, to charge them with wrong, <hi>as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertu. Apol. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra Gentes.</note> 
                  <hi>did,</hi> we haue more neede to prouide you a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine for a cankred mouth, and a ſtincking breath, then to make you any anſwere at all.</p>
               <p>O but, in entring of other countries, there muſt<note place="margin">3. No blood ment to bee ſhed.</note> needes be much lamentable effuſion of bloud. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely our obiecter was hatched of ſome popiſh egge; &amp; it may be in a IESVITS vault, where they feede themſelues fat, with tormenting innocents. Why is there no remedie, but aſſoone as we come<note place="margin">See-white. The way to the Church.</note> on land, like Wolues, and Lyons, and Tygres, long famiſhed, we muſt teare in peeces, murther, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the naturall inhabitants, with cruelties neuer read, nor heard of before? muſt we needs burne mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of them, and caſt millions into the ſea? muſt we baite them with dogges, that ſhall eate vp the mothers with their children? let ſuch be the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the diuell, of <hi>Abaddon the ſonne of perdition,</hi> of Antichriſt and his frie, that is of purple Rome. As for the profeſſors of the Goſpell, they know with<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 47. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Only a ſoiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udg.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. 3. Warres onely defenſiue.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> and his poſteritie, to ſay to <hi>Pharaoh, To ſoiourne in the land are we come; for thy ſeruants haue no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, &amp;c.</hi> They can with <hi>Sampſon</hi> liue peaceably with the Philiſtims, till they bee conſtrained by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11682:12"/> to ſtand vpon their defence. They can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct<note place="margin">Gene. 41. 25. 38</note> the barbarous princes, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Senators; and as <hi>Daniel</hi> did <hi>Nabuchad-ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if theſe obiecters had any braines in their head, but thoſe which are ſicke, they could ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily finde a difference betweene a bloudy inuaſion, and the planting of a peaceable Colony, in a waſte<note place="margin">Onely the Planting of a Peaceable Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie.</note> country, where the people doe liue but like Deere in heards, and (no not in this ſtouping age, of the gray headed world, ful of yeres and experience) haue not as yet attained vnto the firſt modeſtie that was<note place="margin">Gene. 3. 7,</note> in <hi>Adam,</hi> that knew he was naked, where they know no God but the diuell, nor ſacrifice, but to offer their men and children vnto <hi>Moloch.</hi> Can it be a ſinne in <hi>Philip,</hi> to ioyne himſelfe to an Aethiopian charet?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note> Is onely now the ancient planting of Colonies, ſo highly praiſed among the Romans, and all other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo vile and odious among vs, that what is, and hath bene a vertue in all others, muſt be ſinne in vs? And if our obiecter bee deſcended of the Noble Saxons bloud, Let him take heede leſt while he caſt a ſtone at vs, he wounds his father, that firſt brought him in his loynes from forreigne parts into this happie Iſle. But aſſuring my ſelfe that theſe obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters ſpeake that they thinke not, becauſe they think that they ſhould not, and if the tearmes of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were changed, would praiſe other nations for that, which they diſlike in vs: I leaue them to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before his glorious eyes, that all things are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bare vnto, and my ſelfe will paſſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the reſt of our Text vpon the conſciences of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11682:13"/> ſuch, which I hope to bee the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to promiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>ABram muſt get him out, from his country, his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ijo. His Countrey. <hi>Acts 72.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; his fathers houſe.</hi> His Country was called <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> the ſweeteſt, and moſt fruitful ſoyle that was in the worlde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For it lieth betweene the two great riuers <hi>Euphrates</hi> and <hi>Tygris,</hi> which ſerued not,<note place="margin">Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Nat. Hiſt.</note> as other riuers do in other places, to bring fatnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the country: but to ſweepe away the ranknes, and foiſon of the earth, leſt with the luſtineſſe of the ground, the fruit of the earth ſhould rot, or be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or run vp to weed.</p>
               <p>His kindred was euery way of the beſt, and nobleſt<note place="margin">His kindred.</note> ſtocke of the ſonnes of <hi>Noah;</hi> namely the families of<note place="margin">Gene. 9. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Shem,</hi> of whom God ſaid, <hi>Bleſsed be the God of Shem.</hi> So bleſſed were his tents, to wit the houſes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of his poſterity, that, as of the moſt happie thing, it is ſaide; <hi>God perſwade Iapheth,</hi> and his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">27.</note> (of which we are a parte) to <hi>dwell in the tents of Shem.</hi> It ſeemeth then a matter of as greate a perill, to leaue that kindred, as to leaue the church, and ſo ſaluation it ſelfe. So ſaith <hi>Peter to Chriſt: To whome</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 6. 68.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall we goe, thou haſt the words of eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His fathers houſe was worthy for him to haue<note place="margin">His fathers houſe.</note> continued in. For though ſome interpreters think, that he was commanded to remoue, becauſe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe was idolatrous, it is not ſo, It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that they were idolaters, becauſe <hi>Ioſuah</hi> doth ſay, to the children of <hi>Iſraell: your fathers dwelt be yond the floud in olde time, Terah the Father Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24. 2.</note>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:11682:13"/> 
                  <hi>and the Father of Nachor, and ſerued other Gods.</hi> But what of this? Sure it was more through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the law, then through rebellion and rage. For when as <hi>Terah</hi> perceiued, that God was with his ſonne, he left all, without bidding, to go with his ſonne, and had rather put himſelfe in the tents of his ſonne, then want the bleſſing of God. Heereby it appeareth, that they were a very louing people, one to the other, &amp; ſoft harted to obey, when the Lord did commaund. His father alſo was very wealthy, hauing many poſſeſſions, much cattell, a number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and great family of ſeruants, All which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing obſcurely implied in that which was ſpoken of <hi>Abram: Abram was verie rich in cattell, in ſiluer &amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 13. 2. Gene. 14. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>in gold:</hi> and that <hi>when Abram heard that his brother was taken, he armed of them that were borne &amp; brought vp in his howſe, three hundred and eighteene.</hi> For it was not likely but that this wealth, and multitude, came to him from his Father, yet all theſe muſt he forſake, and get him from them, vnleſſe they would follow him and his fortunes (as they ſay) which they might if they wold. Othervviſe if none vvould goe vvith him, but that he muſt be alone; yet muſt he ſtill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv the commandement of his God, that ſaith, <hi>Get thee out from among them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon is giuen by Chriſt, that alſo called<note place="margin">1. Reaſon. The comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is of price, and muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. <hi>Matth. 10. 37.</hi>
                  </note> ſonnes from their fathers, ovvners from their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and lands: brethren from their brethren: fathers, from their children: &amp; husbands from their vviues, as he ſaith. <hi>He that loueth father or mother more then me, is not worthy of me.</hi> The commandement of <hi>God is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11682:14"/> the kingdome of heauen. It is a treaſure hid in the field, a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 13. 44. Pſal. 119. 72. 127.</note> 
                  <hi>pearle of greate price,</hi> vvhich, if hee hath the heart of a man, that findeth, he vvill <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l that he hath, and buy it.</hi> Heere then vvee ſee that, vvhere God giueth a<note place="margin">VSE. Go when God calleth.</note> due vocation to ſpread abroad and inhabit the earth, neither the loue of the country, be it neuer ſo fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; the loue of kindred, bee they neuer ſo noble and holy; the loue of a mans fathers houſe, be the family neuer ſo kinde, ſo rich, ſo numberſome: no nor the largenes of poſſeſſion ought to be any impediment to keepe vs from obedience. Indeede it is true, that if any thing could affoord a man a ſufficient excuſe to deferre obedience vnto Gods commandement, of this kinde, it may bee eaſilie found in one of theſe branches. But vvhat Chriſt ſaith to his follovvers, is to be repeated here: <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith to one <hi>follow mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ſame ſaid, Lord ſuffer me firſt to goe and burie my father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> but Chriſt endureth no delay, for hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſubioineth a ſecond commandement, <hi>Goe thou</hi>
                  <note place="margin">61. 62.</note> 
                  <hi>and preach the kingdome of God: Then another ſaide, I will follow thee Lord; but let me firſt goe, and bid them farewell, which are at mine houſe: And Ieſus ſaide, No man that putteth his hand to the plough and looketh back, is apt to the kingdome of God:</hi> Then the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God muſt needes bee obeyed, whoſoeuer elſe be neglected.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant, that many are not willing to<note place="margin">Reaſon of not going anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. 1. England, not like Meſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamia.</note> goe abroade and ſpread the goſpell, in this moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and chriſtian voyage of the Plantation of <hi>Virginia.</hi> Their reaſons are diuerſe according to their wits. One ſaith, <hi>England</hi> is a ſweete country. True
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11682:14"/> indeede, and the <hi>God of glory be bleſſed,</hi> that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the country was as wilde a forreſt, but nothing ſo fruitfull, as <hi>Virginia,</hi> and the people in their nakednes did arme themſelues in a coate armor of <hi>Woad,</hi> fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching<note place="margin">Com. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſoris.</note> their Curets and Polderns, from a painters ſhop: by the ciuill care of conquerers and planters it is is now become a very paradiſe in compariſon of<note place="margin">Kindred not like Abrams.</note> that it was. But how ſweete ſoeuer it be, I am ſure, it cannot compare with <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>potamia,</hi> where <hi>Abram</hi> dwelt. O but, ſaith another, my kinidred would not be forſaken. Kindred? what kindred? Surely thy kindred is hardly ſo honourable and bleſſed, as the kindred of <hi>Abram</hi> was. And for any thing that I can ſee, ſince ATHEISTS and PAPISTS, haue gotten out of their ſerpents holes, and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with men, they haue ſowed ſuch cockell among our wheate, that in many places a man is in no ſuch perill to be cheated and coſoned, if not murthered &amp; poiſoned, as among his own kindred that are affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that way. Some few, and thoſe very few, are not willing to leaue their fathers houſe, where any thing may bee hoped for after the death of their parents: but for the moſt part, the world perceiueth that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it be to ioyne in a deadly feude, or ſome peece of excellent villanie, the <hi>Engliſh Prouerbe</hi> is true, <hi>The farther from kinne, the neerer to friends.</hi> But look ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly into the land, and ſee whether there bee not iuſt cauſe, if not a neceſſity to ſeek abroad. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note place="margin">Cauſes to ſeeke abroad.</note> bleſſed be God, doe ſwarme in the land, as yong bees in a hiue in <hi>Iune;</hi> inſomuch that there is very hardly roome for one man to liue by another. The
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11682:15"/> mightier like old ſtrong bees thruſt the weaker, as younger, out of their hiues: Lords of Manors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert towneſhips, in which were a hundreth or two hundreth communicants, to a ſhepheard &amp; his dog. The true labouring husbandman, that ſuſteineth the prince by the plow, who was wont to feede manie poore, to ſet many people on worke, and pay twice as much ſubſidie and fifteenes to the king, for his proportion of earth, as his Landlord did for tenne times as much; that was wont to furniſh the church with Saints, the muſters with able perſons to fighte for their ſoueraigne, is now in many places turned labourer, and can hardly ſcape the ſtatute of rogues and vagrants. The gentleman hath gotten moſt of the tillage in his hand; he hath rotten ſheepe to ſell at <hi>Michaelmas:</hi> his ſommer fed oxen at Eaſter: aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no better price for hay, then his beaſts, to keepe that till ſpring, that they got at graſſe: by theſe meanes he can keepe his corne til the people ſterue, alvvaies prouided that the poore husbandmen which are left, and the clothier muſt buy their ſeed, and wool at ſuch a rate, that ſhall vveare them out in a very few yeeres. And were it not, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and chriſtian merchant doth often helpe, who putteth all his eſtate vpon the prouidence of God, which they call venturing, to bring corne into the land, for which he hath many a bitter curſe of the curſed cornmongers, we ſhould finde an extreame famine in the midſt of our greateſt plenty. The rich ſhop-keeper hath the good honeſt poore labourer at ſuch aduantage, that he can grind his facewhen he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11682:15"/> pleaſeth. The poore mettall man vvorketh his bones out, and ſwelteth himſelfe in the fire, yet for all his labour, hauing charge of wife and children, hee can hardly keepe himſelfe from the almes box. Alwaies prouided that his maſters to whom he worketh, will giue neuer a penny towards his liuing; but they can tell of their owne knowledge, that if the poore man were a good husband, he might liue well: for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth much money in the yeere at their hands, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neere foure pence for euery ſixe penny worth of work. The thoughtfull poore woman, that hath her ſmall children ſtanding at her knee, and hanging on her breaſt; ſhe worketh with her needle and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with her fingers, her candle goeth not out by night, ſhe is often deluding the bitternes of her life with ſweete ſongs, that ſhe ſingeth to a heauy heart. Sometimes ſhee ſingeth: <hi>Haue mercie on mee Lorde,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Helpe Lord, for good and godly men doe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and decay:</hi> ſometimes <hi>Iudge and reuenge my cauſe O Lord:</hi> and many ſuch like: which when a man of vnderſtanding doth heare; he doth with pittie praiſe God, that hath giuen ſuch meanes to mocke hunger with, and to giue patience. I warrant you her ſongs want no paſſion; ſhe neuer ſaith, <hi>O Lord,</hi> but a ſalte teare droppeth from her ſorrowfull head, a deep ſigh breatheth as a furnace from her aking hart, that wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vvith the head for company, vvith teares of ſvveeteſt bloud. And vvhen all the vveeke is ended, ſhee can hardly earne ſalt for her vvater gruell to feede on vpon the Sunday. Many ſuch ſvveets are in <hi>England,</hi> vvhich I knovv not how better to interpret
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11682:16"/> then to ſay the ſtrong olde bees doe beate out the younger, to ſvvarme &amp; hiue themſelues elſevvhere. Take the opportunity, good honeſt labourers vvhich indeede bring all the hony to the hiue, God may ſo bleſſe you, that the prouerbe may be true of you, that <hi>A May ſwarme, is worth a kings ranſome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>THE place whither Abram muſt goe, is to the land</hi>
                  <note place="margin">iijo.</note> 
                  <hi>which the Lord will ſet himſee.</hi> A commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fit for God, to perſwade by no arguments ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the ſweetnes and fruitfulneſſe of the place. Thus doth the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> render this place, <hi>By faith Abraham, when he was called, obeyd God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>to goe into a place, which afterwards he ſhould receiue for inheritance, and he went out, not knowing whither hee went.</hi> The like commandement did the Lord giue to the children of Iſrael, when they came out of Egipt: For they muſt not chuſe their owne way, but follow the cloudie piller that led them. For at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Lord, they pitched, and at the<note place="margin">Numb. 9. 23.</note> commaundement of the Lord, they iourneyed, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the watch <hi>of the Lord, at the commaundement of the Lord.</hi> They iourneyed, ſometimes where the waters were bitter, ſometimes where there was no water, ſometimes where the place was full of fierie Serpents, yet could they not be their own chuſers, but muſt follow, where the Lord went before. For<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 34.</note> God in his wayes can endure no counſellour. Hee will be the ſhepheard, we the ſheepe of his paſture,<note place="margin">1. Reaſon. Contented to be Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> He will be the potter, wee muſt content our ſelues with the condition of the potters veſſell: wherefore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11682:16"/> we are bound, if God commaund, to follow him, though blindfold. Againe, the Lord doth not tell<note place="margin">II.</note> him whither he ſhall goe, to keepe him in ſuſpenſe, that the obedience of faith may the more effectually appeare. For if the Lord had enticed him by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments taken from the opportunitie and ſweetneſſe of the place: how ſhould it be knowen, whether hee went by the power of the promiſe of God, or by ſome carnall inducement? We know the diuell ſaith to God of <hi>Iob, Doth</hi> Iob <hi>feare God for nought, haſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 1. 9. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>thou not made a hedge about him &amp; about his houſe?</hi> And we alſo know what Chriſt ſaith to them that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed<note place="margin">Iob 6. 26.</note> him. <hi>Yee ſeeke me not, becauſe yee ſaw the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that is, for any reſpect they had to his Godhead, <hi>but becauſe ye ate of the loaues and were filled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which imputation the Lord would free his ſeruant <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom hee purpoſed to make the Father of the faithfull, and giue him for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all poſteritie. So dealt the Lord in the wilderneſſe with the children of Iſrael: hee let them ſee no poſſibilitie to liue in the world, but ſuſteined them by extraordinary miracle, giuing them <hi>Manna</hi> and <hi>Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> that they might follow the ſteps of their father <hi>Abraham:</hi> and know, that <hi>man liueth not by</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 8. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>bread onely, but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God, doth man liue.</hi> Then here we ſee, where<note place="margin">VSE.</note> God doth commaund,, he is to be obeyed, without asking of any queſtions; <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt goe to a land hee knoweth not whither, becauſe God will haue it ſo. He muſt not ſay, <hi>A Lyon may bee in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtreet,</hi> leſt he find <hi>A Serpent bite him at home, as he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11682:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> on the wall.</hi> How much more, when the land is diſcouered, to bee as much better then the place in which vve liue, as the land of Canaan, was better then the roaring wilderneſſe, ought vve to be vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to goe, vvhither God calleth? The children of<note place="margin">Numb. 14. 7. 8.</note> Iſraell had vvord by their ſpies. <hi>The land which wee walked through to ſearch it, is a very good land. If the Lord loue vs, he will bring vs to this land, and giue it vs, which is a land that floweth with milke and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Thence they brought a <hi>bunch of grapes,</hi> and loaded<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb. 13. 24. Deut.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 24,</note> two men <hi>as they carried it on a barre vpon their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> Sure if ſuch motiues as theſe could not make them readie to runne to the place, it appeared that they had neither the feare of God, that vvould not be perſwaded by him; nor the vvits of reaſonable men, that vvill not reſpect their owne benefit. What ſhall vvee ſay then to our people, vvhich haue in them ſo little edge to follovv their owne thrift. The land, by the conſtant report of all that haue ſeene it, is a good land, with the fruitfulneſſe vvhereof, and pleaſure of the Climate, the plentie of Fiſh and Fowle, England, our miſtreſſe, cannot compare, no not vvhen ſhe is in her greateſt pride. It is ſaid of the land of Canaan, that <hi>Iſaack ſowed in that land, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 26. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>found in the ſame yeere, an hundred fold, by eſtimation:</hi> and the text addeth, <hi>And ſo the Lord bleſſed him.</hi> But here is greater matter then ſo: For, if I count a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, this land giueth fiue hundred fold at one har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. For the <hi>eares of Wheate,</hi> vvhich I haue ſeene, are ten in ſquare, and fiftie long: and yet they ſay, that commonly this returne is little better then the third
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11682:17"/> part, euery ſtalke bearing, ordinarily three ſuch eares of Wheate. As for the opportunitie of the place, I leaue it to the graue Polititian: and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, let the induſtrious Merchant ſpeake: but for foode and raiment, here is inough to be had, for the labour of maſtring and ſubduing the ſoile. The children of Iſraell that were in the wilderneſſe, readie to periſh, if God vvithdrew his miraculous hand, like a ſtiffenec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed people as they were, refuſed to goe, fell into a mutiny, and made a commotion, vpon the newes that the <hi>Land had fenced cities, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 13. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>walled townes exceeding great. And becauſe there were the ſonnes of Anak:</hi> mightie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nts that were armed in Braſſe, &amp; their ſpeare like a Weauers cloth beam. For they forgat the God that brought them out of Egypt, and that made the raging waues of the ſea to ſtand in heapes, and take the office of ſtrong walles, that they might eaſily march through vpon drie land. They forgat that God was the creator of the mountaines, whereof one of the leaſt, is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then all the ſonnes of <hi>Anak.</hi> They forgat that God putteth away all the vngodly of the earth like droſſe. But wee ſhould be worſe then mad, to bee diſcouraged by any ſuch imaginations of this place. There are but poore Arbors for Caſtles, baſe and homely ſheds for vvalled townes. A Mat is their ſtrongeſt <hi>Portcullis,</hi> a naked breſt their Target of beſt proofe: an arrow of reede, on which is no iron, their moſt fearefull vveapon of offence, heere is no feare of nine hundreth iron charets. Their God is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.</note> of mankind <hi>that ſeeketh whom hee may deuoure.</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:11682:18"/> A murtherer from the beginning, that lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ureth<note place="margin">o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n 8. 44.</note> the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe that ſerue him moſt deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Heere that Scripture hath a full accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>In that day ſhall the Lord defend the inhabitants</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>of Ieruſalem, and he that is feeble among them ſhall bee is Dauid,</hi> that ſlew his ten thouſand: <hi>And the houſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>of Dauid as Gods, as the Angel of the Lord before them,</hi> that deſtroyed the moſt puiſſant Armie of the Aſſyrians, that came againſt Ieruſalem. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ay. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſeeing we are contented, when the King doth preſſe vs out to warre, to go we know not whither, nor vnder whom, and can propoſe no thing vnto vs but to fight vvith a mightie enemie: Let vs bee cheerefull to goe to the place, that God will ſhew vs to poſſeſſe in peace and plentie, a Land more like the garden of Eden: vvhich the Lord planted, then any part elſe of all the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Lord doth promiſe to enrich him with many</hi>
                  <note place="margin">iiijo. <hi>Deut. 281. Leuit. 26. 3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>bleſsings, if he be obedient to his calling.</hi> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that ſweete ſanction of the law, vvhen the Lord doth allure men to keepe it, by the abundance of his bleſſings. In this place, the Lord doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> foure moſt excellent mercies, of all men of vnderſtanding moſt earneſtly deſired. The firſt thing he promiſeth vnto him, is, that <hi>The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A great Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord will make him a great Nation.</hi> A thing which in the beginning of the Plantation of the vvorld, by all men, vvas principally deſired, vvith the greateſt lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. Out of this deſire, aroſe the taking of many<note place="margin">Mal. 2. 15.</note> vviues, vvhereas God did make but one. Hence alſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11682:18"/> roſe a reproch vnto the barren, though the Lord had ſhut vp the wombe. This appeareth by <hi>Leah,</hi> who ſaid when ſhe bare a ſonne, <hi>Now therefore my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene 29. 32. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. 1. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>husband will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oue me.</hi> And againe, <hi>Now will my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band keepe me companie, becauſe I haue borne him three ſonnes.</hi> It appeareth alſo by the ſtorie of <hi>Hannah,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>her aduerſary vexed her ſore,</hi> which was her husbands other wife, <hi>for ſhe vpbraided her, becauſe the Lord had made her barren.</hi> It appeareth alſo, that euen to the time of the Goſpel, it was a reproch to a woman if ſhe were barren, as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid when ſhee conceiued with child. <hi>Thus hath the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord dealt with me, in the dayes when he looked on mee, to take from me my rebuke among men.</hi> Yea it was in thoſe dayes a ſpeech, <hi>Curſed bee the barren that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not, and the breaſts that giue not ſucke.</hi> No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile then, if it were an argument very powerfull to perſwade <hi>Abraham</hi> to goe vnder this condition: Eſpecially when <hi>Abraham</hi> was full of yeeres, elder<note place="margin">Gene. 12. 4.</note> then his father was, when he begat him. And alſo<note place="margin">Gene. 18. 11.</note> his wife was well ſtroken in yeeres, in ſo much, that it ceaſed to be with her after the manner of vvomen. And to let it appeare that hee vvas exceedingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected vvith a deſire to multiplie and encreaſe, when God came to him and comforted him, Thus, <hi>Feare</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 15. 1. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>not Abraham, I am thy buckler, and thine exceeding great reward;</hi> he maketh this anſwere to God: <hi>What wilt thou giue me</hi> (for the Text doth ſay hee was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding rich) <hi>ſeeing I goe childleſſe:</hi> As if he had ſaid, that he preferred the bleſſing of multiplication be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the vvorld beſide. Now heere dooth God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11682:19"/> promiſe him, vpon his obedience, not only to giue<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> him a child, or that <hi>he ſhall beget twelue princes,</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Iſmael;</hi> but he <hi>will make him a great Nation;</hi> a Nation, that, not man, but God calleth Great: that is, exceeding great. For imprinting of vvhich<note place="margin">Gene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. Gene. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.</note> promiſe in the heart of <hi>Abraham,</hi> he calleth him to ſee the innumerable ſtarres of the skie, the infinite ſands by the ſea, and the motes of the duſt of the earth, which hee will make fit compariſons to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the greatneſſe of this nation. Then ſeeing,<note place="margin">Anſwere to the Obiection of being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed.</note> whatſoeuer was promiſed to <hi>Abraham;</hi> is alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to all that are of his faith and obedience; here is an anſwere to ſuch, as obiect they are loth to goe from home; becauſe they know not what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them. For if they once get into an other Countrey, they thinke there is an end of them, and all theirs. This the Lord anſwereth; Not ſo, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the commandement, <hi>And God will open the barren wombe, and make her to dwell with a family,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 113. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>and to be a ioyfull mother of children. Prayſe the Lord. Iacob</hi> thus prayſeth God, <hi>with my ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>affe came I ouer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 32. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>this Iorden, and now haue I gotten two bands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond thing vvhich the Lord doth promiſe<note place="margin">God will bleſſe him.</note> vnto <hi>Abram,</hi> is, that <hi>He will bleſſe him, Him</hi> I ſay and the nation that ſhal come of him. What is meant by this bleſſing the Patriarke <hi>Iſake</hi> doth, in part, make plaine, vvhen hee diſpoſeth of this bleſſing to <hi>Iacob</hi> vvhich his Father <hi>Abram</hi> had of God, and left to him. His vvords are theſe. <hi>God giue thee of the dew of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 27. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>and the fatnes of the earth, and plenty of wheat and wine, Let people be thy ſeruants; and nations bow vnto
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11682:19"/> thee, be thou Lord ouer thy brethren, and let thy mothers children honor thee.</hi> In ſumme he bleſſeth him vvith plenty and authoritie. Hovvbeit theſe things vvere but a parte of the bleſſing; the remainder of this bleſſing vvhich indeede is moſt excellent, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſubſtance, vvherof thoſe temporall bleſſings vvere but the type and ſhadovv, and as it vvere the Sacraments. When <hi>Moſes</hi> doth ſay, <hi>My doctrine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall droppe as the raine, and my ſpeech ſhall ſtill as the dew, as the ſhowers vpon the hearbs, and as the greate raine vpon the graſſe.</hi> It is plaine that the devv is but the type of the vvorde of God and his gratious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that doth accompanye it, as all the promiſes vvhich vvere deliuered in a temporall Phraſe had a ſpirituall ſence, To vvhich purpoſe is that in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes, By faith Abraham abode in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 9 10. 16</note> 
                  <hi>land of promiſe, as in a ſtrange countreye, for hee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for a City hauing a foundation, whoſe builder and maker is God, that is an heauenly one,</hi> In this bleſſing then are there all good things, <hi>hauing the promiſe of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>the life preſent, and of that which is to come, for this is the profit, is got by godlines.</hi> So vvhen the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 35.</note> came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> they came forth riche, vvith ſiluer and golde; and vvith greate ſubſtance, as the<note place="margin">Gene. 15. 14.</note> Lord had ſhevved vnto <hi>Abram</hi> before. But that vvas<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 5.</note> not all, for the Lord ſent his angell to accompany them, rayſed them vp Prophets of their brethren, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num. 11. 26 27 1. Cor.</hi> 10. 4. Anſwere to the Obiection of looſing the bleſſing of God.</note> his tabernacle among them, yea ſaith ſaint Paule <hi>They dranke of the ſpirituall rocke that followed them, and the rock was Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And heere is an anſvver to a ſecond obiecton, of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11682:20"/> ſuch as vvill not goe abroad, for feare of looſing the bleſſing of God, diuers are the difficulties into which a man is caſt when hee liueth among barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people. Sure hee cannot haue the bleſſing of <hi>God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is mingled among the heathen.</hi> Hee muſt loſe the preaching of the word of God, and the purity of the Sacraments, thus is he vndone in bodie &amp; ſoule. To this the Lord replieth, that to him that doth wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with the breach of Gods commandement run into tentation, the Lord doth bring vpon him the curſe that <hi>Dauid</hi> forewarneth his ſonne of, <hi>If thou</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Chron. 28. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>forſake him, hee will caſt thee off for euer.</hi> But if a man leaue his Country at Gods commandment, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Lord ſhall euer waite vpon him to feede his body and ſanctifie his ſoule. The trueth is; that none doe ſo ſhine in pietie as thoſe that feare God &amp; are out of their Countrie. We neuer read of ſuch a bleſſing of men, with conſtancie and deliuerance, in their owne Countrie, as we find of ſome abroad. Where did <hi>Sidrach, Miſach, and Abednago,</hi> ſtand<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. 25.</note> for their faith and were deliuered out of the fierie Ouen into which they were caſt, becauſe they would not offend God, but among the <hi>Babilonians?</hi> Where<note place="margin">Dan. 6. 16.</note> did <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhew his conſtancie in prayer, and found deliuerance from the Lyons denne, but among the Gentiles? Stand faſt then in the Faith, and you ſhal ſee the bleſſings of God redoubled vpon you more, being in a ſtrange Contry, then you were able to diſcerne at home.</p>
               <p>The third bleſſing vpon <hi>Abraham,</hi> is, that <hi>God</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A great name.</note> 
                  <hi>will make him a great name.</hi> This is a bleſſing of that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11682:20"/> kinde, as men are exceedingly ambitious of. No meruaile, when God and man doth commend it vnto the world, as a thing of price; <hi>A good name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 7. 3. Prou. 22. 1.</note> (<hi>ſaith Salomon) is better th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n a coſtly oyntment, and is to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e choſen aboue great riches.</hi> Hereupon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath recorded good men; and the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> giueth the reaſon of it, which it rendreth<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 39. 1. Chron. 11.</note> thus, <hi>All theſe, through faith, obtained a good re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>port.</hi> So is <hi>Dauid</hi> regiſtred for a worthie, and ſo are all his worthies recorded by the holy Ghoſt, to ſtirre vp other ages to imitate their vertues, that they may inherit their prayſes, For praiſe for vertue is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing, which Chriſt himſelfe delighted in, His fame was ſpread abroad throughout all the land: and of the fame of the Apoſtles and ſuch as prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Rom. 10. 18.</note> the word of God, Dauid ſaith, which alſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth cite and thus render to their praiſe. <hi>Their ſound went out through all the earth; and their words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ends of the world.</hi> This ſwift flying and loud ſounding fame, doeth the Lord promiſe ſhall bee ſpread abroad of <hi>Abram,</hi> if hee will obey God and forſake his country. A thing which proued true: for all the reſt of the Scriptures, to the end of the Bible hath this onely ſubiect, namely the praiſe of <hi>Abram.</hi> It is certaine that a godly man hath neuer that great name at home, as abroad. Chriſt ſaith truely in the Particular of a Prophet, which is alſo true of euery vertuous man, <hi>A Prophet is not without honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaue in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 13. 57.</note> 
                  <hi>his owne Country, and in his owne houſe.</hi> And ſo here is<note place="margin">Anſwere to the Obiection. of loſſe of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie.</note> an anſwere to a third obiection, which ſome doe make: What ſhould a man do abroad? A man would
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11682:21"/> willingly keepe the poore reputation and reſpect he hath. If I go out of my Country, I ſhall be but ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp among ſtrangers, my memorie will be ſooner rotten abroad, though I liue; then if I were long laide in my graue at home. The Lord anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this obiection thus. Feare not <hi>Abram, I will bee thine exceeding great rewarde,</hi> I will by thee doe ſo greate things in a ſtrange place, that thy name ſhall be remembred, as my name, which I will put vpon thee. Sure it is very true, that manie a man, while he ſtaieth at home, liueth in obſcuritie, as in the darkeſt night, though his vertues and worth deſerue better reſpect. For at home what can bee a mans regarde, where there be millions of his rank, though not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſeruing, yet better fauoured. Get abroad where vertue is ſkant, and there, by the aduancing of thy wiſdome and vertue, thou ſhalt bee more eminent and famous in a yeare, then at home halfe of thy ranke ſhall bee all their daies: hidden vertue is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, but abroade it is magnified, At home bee thou a right good man, thou canſt not be ſeene, for thou art either ouertopt, or ſo many waies equalled, that thou art like Gold in <hi>Salomons</hi> time, vvhich<note place="margin">1. King. 10. 27.</note> vvas eſteemed no better then ſtones, or like Cedars that vvere but like vvild figge trees. Thy vvay then to make the vvorld ring of thy vertue, to thy praiſe among the good, and to the terror of thoſe that are euill, is to go abroad vvhen God calleth thee.</p>
               <p>The fourth bleſſing is that he ſhall be <hi>A bleſsing.</hi> This ſpeech hath relation to the eſteeme that other<note place="margin">A bleſſing.</note> men giue; For ſo doe wee often reade the phraſe in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11682:21"/> the Scripture, where it euer doth import ſo good a reputation among others, that they hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bleſſed for his company. In that ſenſe the prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> vſeth the worde in this ſentence: In<note place="margin">Iſai. 19. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>that day ſhall Iſraell be a third with Egypt and Aſhur, euen a bleſsing in the mids of the land.</hi> And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zacharie</hi> thus, <hi>It ſhall come to paſſe, that as yee were a curſe among the heathen, O houſe of Iudah, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>houſe of Iſrael, ſo will I deliuer you, and ye ſhall bee a bleſsing.</hi> But the ſpeech hath more in it then ſo; namely that whereas, <hi>The time of ignorance God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not:</hi> but that he beſtowed thoſe bleſſing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Acts 17. 30.</note> the barbarons people, by the hand of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall prouidence whereby <hi>he maketh his Sunne to ſhine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 45<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>on the euill, &amp; the good, and ſendeth raine on the iuſt and vniuſt:</hi> now the Lord ſhall beſtow all his bleſſings vpon the land through <hi>Abram:</hi> as if the <hi>Oliue trees</hi> of Gods graces did drop through him, as through a <hi>golden pipe,</hi> vpon them. A greate bleſſing to <hi>Abram</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 4. 12.</note> who herein ſhould be a type of Chriſt. For as of his fullnes all receiue, ſo of <hi>Abram,</hi> the nations ſhould receiue grace for grace. And ſo heere is an anſwer<note place="margin">Anſwere of being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred.</note> to a fourth obiection of them that ſay, what ſhould a man do out of his country? He ſhall bee but a hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and a gaſing ſtocke, and a curſe to thoſe among whom he is a ſtranger. Beſides if hee will haue any good, he muſt ſeeke for pearles in a dunghill, hee muſt lick his hony off from the thorne, and worke his butter out of the fire. Vnto this obiection the Lord anſwereth; <hi>Abram</hi> feare not, for none of theſe things ſhall befall. For on the contrary I wil encline
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11682:22"/> the heart of thy ſtrangers ſo to reſpect thee, that they ſhall holde thee to bee the onely bleſſing that euer came among them, becauſe thou ſhalt verie ſenſibly bring many bleſſings vnto them. When <hi>Iſack</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Abram,</hi> came to <hi>Abimelech,</hi> though<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 26. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> enuied him for his wealth: yet <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> the King came to him with his friends and captaines of his armye, and ſaid, <hi>Wee haue certainely ſeene that the Lord is with thee: and we thought, let there now be an oath betweene vs, and let vs make a couenant with thee, Thou now the bleſſed of the Lord, do this. Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. 38. and 40.</note> 
                  <hi>King of Egypt, ſaid to his ſeruants of Ioſeph, can we find ſuch a man as this, in whom is the ſpirit of God.</hi> He ſaid alſo to <hi>Ioſeph, Thou ſhalt be ouer mine houſe, and at thy word ſhall all my people bee armed.</hi> Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> was knowen to be a bleſſing. Now what the Lord promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> was alſo promiſed to al thoſe<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om.</hi> 4. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that are of the ſame faith and obedience with him. Then this bleſſing, of being a bleſſing, belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoſe which at Gods commandement doe <hi>Get them out of their Country.</hi> When a man of worth is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many men of like worth, he is accounted ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a curſe then a bleſſing, ſuch is the corruption of fleſh and bloud, infected with enuy and with pride. If any good come to any land by reaſon of any good man, yet is there ſuch wreſtling for the garland, that he that hath the moſt friends, will ſet the better leg before, and not onely get the thanks that is due to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; but alſo, as <hi>Iacob</hi> got the ſtart of <hi>Eſau,</hi> in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſo will <hi>Eſau</hi> trip vp the heeles of <hi>Iacob</hi> by his power, if God keepe him not. Nay <hi>Eſau</hi> muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11682:22"/> to haue an Angels face, for winking at his brother; that windeth himſelfe out of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie as cleanly as hee can. But when a man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth abroad, where the word of God and his feare is precious, then euery vertue of worth ſhall haue this <hi>Reſpond</hi> of the <hi>Idiots and Barbarians, out of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>God is in theſe men.</hi> Then can there no bleſſing fall extraordinarily, but all men know for whoſe ſake it is, namely for ſuch as God hath made a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p>Out of theſe arguments, by which God inticed<note place="margin">VSE I.</note> 
                  <hi>Abram</hi> to goe out of his Country, ſuch as goe to a Chriſtian Plantation may gather many bleſſed leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.<note place="margin">Marrie not with Infidels.</note> 
                  <hi>God will make him a greate nation.</hi> Then muſt <hi>Abrams</hi> poſteritie keepe them to themſelues. They may not marry nor giue in marriage to the heathen, that are vncircumciſed. And this is ſo plaine, that out of this foundation aroſe the law of marriage a-among themſelues. The breaking of this rule, may breake the neck of all good ſucceſſe of this voyage, whereas by keeping the feare of God, the Planters in ſhorte time, by the bleſſing of God, may grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a nation formidable to all the enemies of Chriſt, and bee the praiſe of that part of the world, for ſo ſtrong a hand to bee ioyned with the people here that feare God.</p>
               <p>Another thing alſo is to bee marked out of this<note place="margin">II. A great Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> place, mamelie, that to grow into a great nation is a very great bleſſing of God. Then are they but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, that hold a great family of children to bee a heauie and ſore charge: and they blaſpheme they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:11682:23"/> knovv not what, that wiſh God had their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for they could ſpare them well enough. But eſpecially <hi>the ſonne of perdition,</hi> that body of Poperie is by this Text made abhominable, that once wrote to the Lords of the Counſell of this Land, that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie would much profit the Land, becauſe by the ſingle life of Prieſts and Nunnes, and Monkes, and Friers, the Common-wealth ſhould not be ſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with multitude of children. They fitly ſay, not charged; but they ſay not, that leſſe children ſhall be gotten. For when as one fiſhponde, a thouſand<note place="margin">Par. Vrſperg.</note> yeares agoe, could affoorde more then ſixe thouſand infants heads, ſo long before <hi>the abſtruſe ſtudies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> came from hell into the hands of <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> what ſhall wee thinke of theſe latter daies? But to rake no further into that ſtinking kennell, I muſt tell them to their teeth, that when they ſay the kingdome is better for the ſmallnes of the number of the ſubiects, or is not the better for being a great nation, that they doe like their father the diuell, giue God the lie.</p>
               <p>Whereas God doeth promiſe to bleſſe him in<note place="margin">III.</note> his Iourney, as hee did indeede, giuing him the gift<note place="margin">Bleſſe his Iourney.</note> of a Prophet to teach, of a Prieſt to pray, of a King to rule, of plentie in his Temporall eſtate, and Ioye in ſeeing Chriſt the Sauiour of his ſoule; here may<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 56.</note> ſuch as tranſplant at Gods commandement, bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of that promſe of God, <hi>I will not leaue thee, nor forſake thee;</hi> but as God ſaith to <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> as I was with <hi>Moſes ſo will I be with thee:</hi> ſo God ſaith to<note place="margin">Ioſh 1. 5.</note> them, as I was with <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo will I be with you. <hi>I will bleſſe you,</hi> to wit, with the bleſſings of this life
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11682:23"/> and of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>But further if you will haue <hi>Abrams</hi> bleſsing, you<note place="margin">IIII.</note> muſt doe your diligence to walke in thoſe wayes, by which the Lord doeth giue his bleſsings. You muſt not with Idleneſſe, inforce God to worke my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of mercie on the wilfully ſinfull. You muſt bee diligent to heare the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reuerent in beleeuing and receiuing of it, fruitfull in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an practiſe of it, that the bleſsing of God may come vpon you. God can raiſe children vnto <hi>Abraham of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>the very ſtones,</hi> and caſt you away if you caſt him off.</p>
               <p>In that the Lord doeth promiſe <hi>Abraham</hi> to make<note place="margin">V.</note> him a great Name, know that it is a bleſſed thing to<note place="margin">A good Name</note> be well ſpoken of. This will God bring vpon the obedient. But if you diſobey, you will but make the eares of them to tingle, that heare of you. And as we are in continuall expectation of ſome honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable effect, if you continue in the faith: ſo will you bring a confuſion vpon your ſelues, and a ſhame vpon your Nation, if you ſticke not faſt to God, and his bleſſed commaundements.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, whereas God doth promiſe, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi>
                  <note place="margin">VI.</note> ſhall be a bleſſing, you muſt know it your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 15. 16.</note> to walke wiſely towards <hi>thoſe that are without, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the time, becauſe the dayes are euill.</hi> The dayes are euill indeede, in that continent.</p>
               <p>Then how tender ought your care to be, to gaine the reputation of a bleſſing among this people. Let them ſee, that he that came before, was but Satan whom they themſelues doe ſerue, <hi>that had transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. Cor</hi> 11. 13. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe into an Angell of light; and that they were
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11682:24"/> Satans miniſters, that transformed themſelues into the Apoſtles of Chriſt. But walke you honeſtly as in the day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 11. atth. 5. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie you father which is in heauen. While we haue time, let v doe good to all men; yet giue</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal 6. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phe. 4. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>no place to the diuell.</hi> So the bleſſing of God ſhall be vpon vs, and we ſhall be a bleſſing whereſoeuer we goe. And ſtill remember that, as the diuels children will needs be a curſe, ſo the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham</hi> will alwayes labour to be a ſweete bleſſing, where euer they come. And theſe were the arguments that concerned <hi>Abraham</hi> and his people, wee muſt novv proceed alſo to ſpeake of ſuch arguments that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Lord doth deale wonderfully with him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi>
                  <note place="margin">V<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> 
                  <hi>of others,</hi> When he is departed from his owne Countrie. For firſt the Lord will <hi>bleſſe them that bleſſe him.</hi> To bleſſe, in this place, is by word and deed to ſeeke the proſperitie of any. The Lord then doth promiſe to make all his bleſſings goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, that doe, in any manner, make their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings goe before his ſeruants. To this purpoſe is it, which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> hath, <hi>Pray for the peace of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem, Let them proſper that loue thee.</hi> And that of Chriſt. <hi>He that receiueth a Prophet, in the name of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>att. 10. 41. 42</note> 
                  <hi>a Prophet, ſhall receiue a Prophets reward; and hee that receiueth a righteous man, in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receiue the reward of a righteous man. And whoſoeuer ſhall giue to one of theſe little ones, to drinke, a cup of cold water onely, in the name of a Diſciple. Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11682:24"/> I ſay vnto you, he ſhall not looſe his reward.</hi> Vpon this bleſſing of God was it that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid to his ſonne <hi>Salomon. Shew kindnes vnto the ſonnes of</hi> Barzillai <hi>the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 2. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Gileadite,
- for ſo they came to me, when I fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom <hi>thy brother.</hi> And as the Lord doth bleſſe them that loue his children, with his bleſſings of this life, ſo doth he bleſſe them at laſt with the kingdome of heauen. For thus doth our Sauiour Chriſt giue his ſentence; <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, take the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the kingdome prepared for you, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>of the world: For I was an hungred, and ye gaue me meat, &amp;c.</hi> Which afterwards he doth thus explaine, <hi>Verely I ſay vnto you, in as much as ye haue done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren ye haue done it to me.</hi> But here we muſt vnderſtand, that when he ſaith, I will bleſſe them that bleſſe <hi>thee,</hi> the word <hi>thee,</hi> did not ſignifie perſonall <hi>Abraham;</hi> but <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his poſteritie, which were in his loynes, and were to be that great Nation, that the Lord promiſed to make of him. And this, the Foxe <hi>Balam</hi> knew very<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 24 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> well, when ſpeaking of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the habitation of Iſrael, He citeth this Text: <hi>Bleſſed is hee that bleſſeth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. and 39 23.</note> 
                  <hi>thee. Laban</hi> was bleſſed for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake, and the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the priſon, with his whole charge, was bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed becauſe of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> The midwiues, that did ſpare<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. 20. 21.</note> the children of the Iſraclites, and did not kill them, according to the commaundement of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the king, were alſo bleſſed: which the Scripture doth thus record, <hi>God therfore proſpered the widowes.</hi> And againe, <hi>And becauſe the widowes feared God, therefore he made them houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rahab</hi> alſo, that harboured and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11682:25"/> hid the Lords ſpies, found the bleſſing that <hi>Ioſhuah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 14. &amp; 6. 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaued her, and her fathers houſhold, and all that ſhe had, and ſhe dwelt in Iſrael,</hi> as it ſeemeth, married to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and ſo alſo from her came Chriſt.</p>
               <p>To curſe, in this place, doth ſignifie all kind of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut. 28. Leuit.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> as appeareth by the lawe of God. And ſo the meaning is, that the Lord will ſpend all his plagues vpon ſuch as doe bring any affliction vpon <hi>Abraham,</hi> yea the Lord will reuenge them in his wrath. So ſaith the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>He that ſhall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>offend one of theſe little ones, that beleeue in me, it were better for him, that a milſtone were hanged about his necke: and that he were drowned in the depth of the ſea.</hi> Let <hi>Pharaoh</hi> tell how well he ſped for taking <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hams wife into his houſe,</hi> The Text ſaith, <hi>The Lord plagued Pharaoh with great plagues; becauſe of Sarai A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brahams</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 12 15. 12. Gen. 20. 3. 18. Ge. 19. 5. 12. 24. Exod. 1. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>wife.</hi> Let <hi>Abimelech</hi> tell, how much better he faired for the like pranke. But <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dom</hi> will neuer be forgotten, that would abuſe ſtrangers. And E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt is hanged vp a table, in all mens eyes, to let them ſee, that the Lord hath innumerable fearefull plagues, to ſpend vpon them that will deale craftily, and cruelly with his people; and not ſuffer them to ſerue the Lord. The reaſon hereof is, that God, to<note place="margin">Reaſon, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God. <hi>Gen. 17. 7.</hi>
                  </note> him that receiueth his couenant, doth bind himſelfe to be his God, <hi>and the God of his ſeede.</hi> And thus the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> bringing foorth God expreſsing his meaning to be, that there is ſo ſtrickt an Vnion, betweene God and his people, that what is done to his ſeruants, hee taketh as done to himſelfe; His words be theſe, <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 2. 8.</note>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:11682:25"/> 
                  <hi>of mine eye.</hi> To this purpoſe is that of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>He that receiueth you, receiueth me: and he that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>receiueth me, receiueth him that ſent me.</hi> And againe, <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me: and he that deſpiſeth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 10. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> And now, ſeeing the reſpect of bleſſing or curſing, which falleth vpon <hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſteritie, doth fall vpon God, then conſider what God ſaith for himſelfe. <hi>Them that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>me, I will honour: and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed.</hi> And this doth <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledge in God, <hi>With the godly, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelfe godly: with the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 25. 26</note> 
                  <hi>vpright, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelfe vpright: with the pure, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelfe pure: and with the froward, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelfe froward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is then to bee obſerued, that godly men, that<note place="margin">VSE. I.</note> feare God, where euer they goe by Gods vocation,<note place="margin">Godly men find friends.</note> they ſhall find friends, and ſuch as ſhall bleſſe them. He made <hi>thoſe that led them away captine to pitie them. Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> found more honour abroad, then their Princes had at home. <hi>Eſter</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> found more fauour at <hi>Shuſan,</hi> then many of their better found at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Hee that raiſed vp thoſe godly men friends abroad, will alſo prouide for you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, if ye continue his faithfull ſeruants, as <hi>Abram</hi> did. And further, here wee ſee, that ſuch as loue<note place="margin">II.</note> Gods people ſhall proſper; though they be but hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.<note place="margin">The friends of godly men proſper.</note> This may giue warrantie vnto our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to accept of fauour and bleſſings, euen of the Gentiles: and alſo to hold a league and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, euen with the well affected Heathen, that God hath ſtirred vp, to be the means of his Bleſſings
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11682:26"/> vnto vs. So is it ſaid to <hi>Abram,</hi> When he had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to reſcue his brother <hi>Lot</hi> from <hi>Chedor-Laome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Then came one that eſcaped, and told</hi> Abram <hi>the Ebrew, which dwelt in the plaine of Mamre, the Amorite, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to</hi> Eſhcol, <hi>and brother to</hi> Aner, <hi>which were confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with Abram.</hi> And alſo we may ſecure our ſelues, in the aſſociation of ſuch; that God will not kill vs for their ſakes: but on the contrary, <hi>God will bleſſe them</hi> for our ſakes.</p>
               <p>Againe, this text doth teach vs thus much, that<note place="margin">III.</note> in a ſtrange Countrey, we muſt looke for enemies;<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt looke for ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> euen curſing enemies, vnder whoſe tongues is the poyſon of Aſpes, and whoſe right hand is a right hand of iniquitie. <hi>Balaam,</hi> that had a witches tongue<note place="margin">Ioſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Num. 22. 6.</note> in his head, was ſent for to curſe Iſrael, by <hi>Balak,</hi> that knew he had a peſtilent tongue. The ſeed of the diuel<note place="margin">Gen 3. 15.</note> will be ſpighting and biting, doe what a man can. This our Sauiour foretelleth to his holy Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Iohn 16. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>In the world you ſhall haue trouble.</hi> A thing which if the children of Iſrael had knowen as they ought, they would neuer haue refuſed to enter the land which God commanded them to poſſeſſe: becauſe there were curſing and killing enemies, no better then Canibals. Bee not then diſcouraged, though you light on enemies: for that did God foretell vnto <hi>Abram,</hi> that hee and his ſeed muſt find. Rather bee ſtrong, and of good courage: becauſe the Lord is with you; and with them, but an arme of fleſh.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, our text doth tell vs, that he will curſe<note place="margin">IIII.</note> them that curſe <hi>Abram,</hi> This the witch <hi>Balaam</hi> knew<note place="margin">Their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall be curſed.</note> that if any would open his mouth to curſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11682:26"/> of God, hee ſhould bee curſed himſelfe: for the curſe ſhould returne vnto him, as <hi>Water into his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 109. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>bowels, and oyle into his bones.</hi> And generally, they ſhall come vnto ſhame and confuſion, as many as haue euill will at <hi>Ziion.</hi> Here then is a warrant that where godly men are conſtrained to encounter with curſers, ſuch as are the Prieſts of the Gentiles; it is Gods ordinance to bring a curſe vpon them, and to kill them: as the children of Iſrael did <hi>Balam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13. 22.</note> Here is alſo a promiſe, that, if we keepe our ſelues to <hi>Abrams</hi> faith and obedience, God will bring a curſe vpon all our enemies. The Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> hath many excellent ſpeeches, to expreſſe this by: <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will make Ieruſalem a cup of poyſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto all the people in the ſiege of Ieruſalem. Ieruſalem ſhall bee a heauie ſtone for all people: all that lift at it, ſhall be torne; though all the earth be gathered together againſt it.</hi> Againe, <hi>the princes of Iuda ſhall bee as coles of fire among wood, and like the firebrand in the ſheafe, and they ſhall deuoure all people round about, on the right hand, and on the left.</hi> Theſe things ſpake the Prophet of theſe victorious dayes of the Goſpell. I hope out of theſe words thus generally deliuered, euery true hearted Proteſtant, can frame out an anſwere vnto the obiection, that is thought much to impeach this Plantation in VIRGINIA. The perill, ſay the obiecters, is great by the Papiſts that ſhall come on the backe of vs. What Papiſts doe you feare? the Princes? Sure, ſuch as are in aliance with our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will thinke other thoughts, and take better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. But as for the popiſh Church, an vnruly beaſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11682:27"/> exempt from all good gouernment, Ciuill and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, onely adoring him, that <hi>hath exalted himſelfe aboue all that is called God, or that is worſhipped,</hi> it may be they, like the daughters of <hi>Salomons</hi> horſleaches, will cry, <hi>Giue, giue, more blood, and yet more bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 14. 15.</note> And yet, a man would thinke, they were glutted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time of day, <hi>For in her may be found the blood</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eue.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>of the Prophets and of the Saints, and of</hi> ALL <hi>that were ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine vpon the earth.</hi> But you will ſay, now they be ſo well fleſhed, they will haue more blood. To this firſt our text anſwereth in general, neuer feare them: they come to curſe with Bell, Booke and Candle, and the Diuell and all: but remember this, <hi>God will cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe them that curſe Abram.</hi> But ſay you, they are ſuch terrible beaſts, as that the profeſſors of the Goſpell muſt needes be afraid of them. Indeed their perill was great, while their <hi>Inchauntments</hi> were in<note place="margin">Reue. 18. 23.</note> force. <hi>Iannes and Iambres withſtood Moyſes,</hi> till the<note place="margin">Exod. 9. 11.</note> Plague of the <hi>Scab</hi> fell vpon them, and then they were able to ſtand before <hi>Moyſes</hi> no longer. So they<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reue.</hi> 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> iuggled, and did many ſtrange tricks, and much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, till the Plague of the <hi>Scab</hi> light vpon them at <hi>Naples,</hi> more then an hundred yeere agoe: but ſince, though their induſtrie hath bene nothing inferior to the diuels, that <hi>came from compaſsing of the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>to and fro;</hi> yet they may caſt a wofull accompt: For they find in the total<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, how many Kingdomes they haue loſt, and doe daily loſe; how many battailes they haue fought, in all which to the Proteſtants, as the Cananites, would proue to the Iſralites in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebs</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.</note> iudgement, ſo haue they bene, euen <hi>Bread for vs.</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:11682:27"/> Aske what is become of thoſe imperiall armies, that went into Boeme, againſt the Huſsites, in the time of <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperour: and know, what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of their Armour: whether it armed not the Huſsites that wanted? Aske what is become of the many ſhippes that came into the Narrow ſeas in the yeere 1588? I am ſure much of their Ordinance furniſhed the Netherlanders. Will they come to you? Sure GOD that made Iſrael rich of the ſpoiles of Egypt, can by his prouidence make them furniſh you with ſhippes, with Munition, with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, with money: let this be your hope. But feare not their feares. Babilon, ſaith the Angell, is fallen;<note place="margin">Reue. 14. &amp; 18</note> neuer to riſe againe: ſing <hi>Hallelu-iah,</hi> and you ſhall ſee her ſmoake aſcend for euermore. No, no, they<note place="margin">Reue. 19. 3.</note> ſhall preuaile no more, <hi>for their madnes is made eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 8.</note> They haue another chare to doe, I hope, will make them ſcratch where it itcheth not. Thinke ye that it is poſsible for Princes, whoſe treaſure is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, and honour impeached, by their inchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not to require ſatisfaction for theſe wrongs? and, to that purpoſe, pull all their Mammon from vnder their Altars? I am perſwaded, the Armour they haue in the roufes of their Churches, will one day helpe to arme a company of good fellowes, that will come to Church, it may bee vnder pretence of hearing a Maſſe, but will depart with good luggage, of ſiluer and gold, and pearle, and ſuch like, that is there ready gathered to their hands. Wherefore feare God, and of all others, there lieth the leaſt feare to be looked for from them. The onely perill is in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11682:28"/> offending God, and taking of Papiſts in to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: if once they come creeping into your houſes, then looke for miſchiefe: if treaſon or poyſon bee of any force: know them all to be very Aſſaſines, of all men to be abhorred. But hope in God that hee, that hath ſent you abroad, will alſo ſend you ſuch gouernours, as will caſt out the <hi>leauen out of your houſes:</hi> to whom I need ſay little, becauſe I know they need not be nurtured by me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>IN Abram ſhall all the families of the earth bee bleſſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> By <hi>Abram,</hi> is ment, as before, <hi>Abraham,</hi> as in his loynes are many nations. For that which is heere ſpoken of <hi>Abram,</hi> is alſo ſpoken of <hi>Iacob,</hi> in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>In thee, and in thy ſeed, ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> It is true that in <hi>Abraham</hi> and his<note place="margin">Gen. 28. 14.</note> Children, were many men bleſſed: as appeareth in the Scripture, where they haue drawne many ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to ſerue God. Howbeit the principall bleſſing is aſcribed to Chriſt, who by excellencie is called <hi>Thy ſeede;</hi> as S. <hi>Paule</hi> doth very notably obſerue, when he ſaith, <hi>Hee ſaith not, and to thy ſeedes, as ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>of many, but, And to thy ſeed, as of one, which is Chriſt.</hi> By the families of the earth are vnderſtood all thoſe nations, which aroſe from the <hi>families of the ſonnes of Noah, after their generations among their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>people; for out of theſe were the nations diuided in the earth after the flood:</hi> and that which is heere rendred families, afterward is called <hi>Nations</hi> in the ſpeech of the Lord of <hi>Abraham, All the nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed in him. S. Paul</hi> rendreth it thus, in <hi>thee ſhall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8. &amp; 22. 18.</note>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:11682:28"/> 
                  <hi>all the Gentiles be bleſſed.</hi> By bleſſing in this place, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 8.</note> the ſeed is Chriſt, and the word, <hi>Thee,</hi> did ſo far point out <hi>Abraham,</hi> as it had relation to <hi>Chriſt in his loynes,</hi> of force it muſt ſignifie that bleſſedneſſe, which Chriſt doth bring vnto men. Which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel <hi>and a multitude of heauenly ſouldiers,</hi> do compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in their ſweete ſong of praiſing God, when they ſaid. <hi>Glorie be to God on high, and Peace on earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and towards men good will.</hi> Then the ſpeech, all put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, is this, that <hi>Abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ham</hi> muſt get him out of his Countrie: that he may begin that, which God, by him and his ſeed, will accompliſh in due time: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that all nations may embrace the goſpel of Chriſt vnto their ſaluation. An excellent argument, and of ſingular force, to perſwade not only <hi>Abram,</hi> but all his Children according to the faith, to fly, if it were poſſible, ouer the mountaines, about ſo greate an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. O with what Comfort may a man come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, with this account of his talent. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am heere, &amp; the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which God hath geuen me.</hi> It would neuer grieue S <hi>Paule</hi> to go from <hi>Cilicia,</hi> to preſent a Church at <hi>Corinth, a pure Virgin to Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Obiection. The laſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at hand.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtay, ſaith one, you run too faſt without good ground: you ſeeme to encline to the Millenaries, or ſuch as looke for the goſpell to be ſpread ouer all the world. You muſt know that is done manie a faire yeare agoe, that we need not looke for a new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution of that. It were ſafer to tremble at the laſt iudgement, whoſe trumpet is euer ſounding in our eares: <hi>Ariſe from the dead and come to iudgement.</hi> To this I anſwere that no preiudicate opinion is a iuſt<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:11682:29"/> condemnation to the trueth, nor any doctrine out of Bookes that are <hi>Apocripha,</hi> can make a wiſe man depart from a doctrine of the <hi>Canonicall Scriptures.</hi> It is true that <hi>Gregories</hi> credit was wont to bee great<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. lib. Dialo.</note> in the times that men knew no better, who confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affirmed the iudgement to bee at hand; but beſides the confutation of a thouſand yeares, which haue bin ſince hee ſo affirmed, the pregnant &amp; cleere Scripture confoundeth the proud coniecture of him and his followers. And this doth alſo appeare by the Apoſtaſie of ſome Papiſts that in their bookes<note place="margin">Maluenda de Antichristo.</note> lately Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> haue departed from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſo great a Pope, and graue Doctor of the Church, telling vs plainely that the goſpell muſt be preached vniuerſally through the world before the laſt Iudgement. But neither by their authority, nor arguments, but by the force of ſuch Texts as cannot be deluded, do I affirme, <hi>That all the Nations of the world ſhall be bleſſed in Chriſt.</hi> They that mince and pare this Text, that they make it as ſore as the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamits</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 34. 25. Pſal. 19. 3. Rom. 10. 18.</note> were with their circumciſion, ſay, that, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ouerlaſhing hyperbole, and, <hi>Their ſound is gone out into all the world,</hi> will ſerue the turne. A ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bleſſing God knoweth and little differeth from <hi>The ſauor of death vnto death. If they receaue you not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 3. 16.</note> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt,) ſhake off the duſt of your feete. Truely, I ſay vnto yon, it ſhall be eaſier for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of Iudgement, then for that Citie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10. 14.</note> howſoeuer they heard the ſound of the worde of God. This ſtumbling blocke, fewe wiſe men will ſay was this <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> promiſed to <hi>Abram.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:11682:29"/>
               <p>The Iewes hunt counter as faſt on the other ſide, For when as, in the ſecond <hi>Pſalme,</hi> they reade of their <hi>Meſstas,</hi> that <hi>he ſhall haue the heathen for his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the vtter moſt parts of the earth for his poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 8. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>that he ſhall cruſh them with a ſcepter of yron, and breake them in peeces like a potters veſſel,</hi> they affirme, that all the world muſt bee ſubdued by force and violence vnto <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> An opinion that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed much in the time of Chriſt, as appeareth not onely by diuerſe others, but alſo by the Apoſtles, who encountred our Sauior Chriſt thus, before his aſcenſion. <hi>Lord wilt thou at this time reſtore the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 1. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>to Iſrael.</hi> But they alſo make but an vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable bleſsing of this bleſſednes of <hi>Abraham.</hi> The phraſe is plaine, that in <hi>Abraham all the families of the earth ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> A bleſſednes then muſt the Gentiles truſt to receiue from <hi>Abraham.</hi> Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe things are deliuered in the Scripture, which, I thinke, no diſtinctions <hi>of hyperbole,</hi> nor <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> nor <hi>at the laſt iudgement,</hi> can delude, which are the ordinary refuges of them that, out of preiudice, would faine put by the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniell</hi> hath it thus, <hi>A ſtone was cut without hands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſmote the image vpon the feete, and brake them in peeces. Then was the yron, the clay the braſſe, the ſiluer, and gold broken together, and became like chaffe of the ſummer flowers, and the winde carried them away, that no place was found for them: and the ſtone, that ſmot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the image, became a greate mountaine, and filled the whole earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, firſt, we plainly ſee, that Chriſt muſt deſtroy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:11682:30"/> the Monarches that they be not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And ſo much of this ſpeech doth S. <hi>Paul</hi> interprete thus plainely. <hi>That Chriſt ſhall put downe all rule, and all authoritie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, 15. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 25. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and power. For he muſt reigne, till hee ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h put all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, vnder his ſeete: the laſt enemy that ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed is death,</hi> The other part of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Dauid</hi> doth thus expreſſe in the <hi>Pſalme. Thou Lorde</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalt inherit all nations.</hi> And this point the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> doth render thus. <hi>The Lord ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll bee King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the earth, In that day there ſhall be one Lord, and his name ſhall be one:</hi> ſo that no other God ſhall bee<note place="margin">Zach. 14. 19.</note> named in all the worlde. But leſt any ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this point of the laſt iudgement, and ſo place earth in heauen; <hi>Daniell</hi> ſheweth how the Lord ſhall be king, his words are theſe. <hi>The kingdome and dominion, and greatnes of his kingdome vnder the whole</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>heauen ſhall be giuen to the holy people of the moſt high, whoſe kingdome is an euerlaſting kingdome, and alpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall ſerue and obey him.</hi> But what ſhal he aboliſh kings, and bring all to a Popularity? no ſuch matter, <hi>God is the author of order; and not of confuſion. The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Cor. 14. 33 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>euel.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>kingdomes of this world ſhall bee our Lords, and his Christs, and hee ſhall raigne for euermore,</hi> by Kings conuerted to the Goſpell. For godly Kings <hi>doe ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 30. 23 Pſa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. &amp; 97. &amp; 99.</note> 
                  <hi>on the throne of the Lord, and by them the Lord reigneth</hi> The beginning of this alteration <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expreſſeth thus. <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queenes ſhall be thy nurſes: they ſhall worſhip thee with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 49. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>towards the earth, and licke vp the duſt of thy feete.</hi> But leaſt any man ſhould ſay, it may bee ſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but what is that to the reſt? <hi>Dauid</hi> anſwereth thus, <hi>The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11682:30"/> Kings of Tarſhiſh, and of the Iles ſhall bring preſents. The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings of Sheba, and Seba, ſhall bring gifts, yea All</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 47. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings ſhall worſhip him, All nations ſhall ſerue him.</hi> And againe, <hi>The Lord is high and terrible: A great King ouer all the earth.</hi> And again in the ſame <hi>Pſalme. God is King ouer all the earth, ſing praiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, whoſoeuer hath vnderſtanding. God reigneth ouer the heathen &amp;c.</hi> If any do yet think that they ſhall ſerue him as the Kings did <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> when he ſet his feet on their necks:<note place="margin">Ioſh. 10. 24.</note> the bleſſed ſcripture ſaith no. For the <hi>Pſalme</hi> hath it thus. <hi>All Kings of the earth ſhall praiſe thee, O Lord, for</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 138. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>they haue heard the words of thy mouth.</hi> A thing which they will not doe at the reſurrection; when going to hell thy ſhall ſay: <hi>When ſaw we thee an hungred, or a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>thirſt, or a ſtranger, or naked, or ſicke or in priſon &amp;c?</hi> And as the ſcripture is very particular in ſetting down the ſtate of the kings, how they ſhall ſtand af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Goſpell, ſo doth it of the people. Firſt<note place="margin">Pſal. 97. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith <hi>All the people ſhall ſee thy glory.</hi> But that is not ſufficient, wherefore S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> in the Reuelation goeth farther thus. <hi>All nations ſhall come and worſhip</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 15. 5. Iſai. 45. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>before thee, O Lord.</hi> Iſaiah hath it thus,, <hi>I haue ſworne by my ſelfe, and the worde is gone out of my mouth in righteouſnes, and ſhall not returne: that euery knee ſhall bow vnto mee, and euery tongue ſhall ſweare by mee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 9. 10.</note> Which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth thus. <hi>God hath exalted Chriſt Ieſus and giuen him a name aboue all names: that at the name of Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould euery knee bow, and that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tongue ſhould confeſſe that Ieſus is the Lord, vnto the glory of God the Father. Malachie</hi> yet goeth further<note place="margin">Mala<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 11.</note> thus: <hi>From the riſing of the Sun, to the going downe of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:11682:31"/> the ſame, My name is great among the Gentiles, and in euery place incenſe ſhall be offred vnto thy name, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>a pure offring.</hi> The <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſaith alſo, <hi>The princes of the people are gathered vnto the people of the God of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> To conclude this point the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith <hi>From moneth to moneth, and from Saboth, to Saboth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall all fleſh come to worſhip me; ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumme is, what bleſſing any Nation had by Chriſt, muſt be Communicated to all Nations: the office of his Prophecie to teach the ignorant; the office of his Prieſthood, to giue remiſſion of ſinnes to the ſinnefull: the office of his kingdome, by word, and Sacraments, and ſpirit, to rule the inordinate: that <hi>ſuch as are dead in treſpaſſes, may be made to ſit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 1. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>in heauenly places. For there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Iew, and the Grecian. For he that is Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>all, is rich vnto all, that call vpon him.</hi> For it well beſeemeth the glory of God to triumph ouer his<note place="margin">Reaſons from Gods attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes.</note> enemies: and the Wiſdome of God (after the world hath had plentifull experience of the craft of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and wicked men of all ſortes) to exalte the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>the wiſedome of God:</hi> As alſo his Power to bee declared, when all his enemies had ſhewed their force; and his Mercy to his Saints, after ſo great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of patience; and his iuſtice, to ſhewe his iudgements, in condemning thoſe that haue ſpoken proud words, and done wicked deeds, to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. But eſpecially to his Glory, in exalting his ſonne, and crowning him with Glory, &amp; Worſhip, that we may ſee that, which yet we ſee not: <hi>All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings be put in ſubiection vnto him.</hi> It is true that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">
                     <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b.</hi> 2. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:11682:31"/> obiections are made againſt this doctrine, out of ſuch places as this. <hi>When the ſonne of man commeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall he finde faith on the earth?</hi> And of <hi>Antichriſt, whom</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord ſhall aboliſh, by the brightneſſe of his comming.</hi> But partly, for want of Grammer learning, to know the meaning of the word <hi>Come,</hi> and partly for want of Logick, to lay out thoſe places to their due times: thoſe Scriptures, and many more, are racked by ſuch men out of their ioints: which rightly vnderſtood, haue a cleane other ſenſe, then that for which they are alleadged: which neither this time nor place will giue me leaue to diſpute. Wherefore ſtanding to our owne firſt grounde, learne firſt to bee ſparing in<note place="margin">VSE.</note> abridging the glory of God; which made the world,<note place="margin">Be ſparing in ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ning the glory of God.</note> that his Sonne might rule ouer all. For howſoeuer, for ſome good cauſes, God would not make himſelf glorious at the firſt, but would ſeeme to hide the glory of God in the paſſion of his Sonne, and afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Saints; and permitting <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to clime to his height, that thoſe that are perfect may be knowne: yet queſtionleſſe, <hi>Chriſt must ſit at the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. Cor. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>right hand of his Father, till all his enemies bee made his footeſtoole,</hi> and then ſhall come from thence to iudge the quick and the dead.</p>
               <p>Againe, if it be Gods purpoſe, that the Goſpell<note place="margin">II.</note> ſhall be preached through the world for a witneſſe, then ought miniſters to bee carefull and willing to ſpread it abroad, in ſuch good ſeruices as this, that is intended. Sure it is greate ſhame vnto vs, of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, that can be better content, to ſit, and reſt vs heere idle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then vndergoe ſo good a worke. Our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:11682:32"/> of zeale, is cleare diſcouered to be but hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, when we rather chooſe to minde vnprofitable queſtions at home, then gaining ſoules abroad. It is a ſingular ſin for men to be ouercome with euill, it is a ſhame that the Ieſuites and Friers, that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euery ſhip, ſhould be ſo diligent to deſtroy ſouls, and wee not ſeeke the tender lambes, nor bind vp that which is broken.</p>
               <p>But go on couragiouſly, and notwithſtanding the ſnorting idlenes of the miniſtery, ſuſpect not the<note place="margin">2 King. 5. 2.</note> bleſsing of God. A captiue girle, brought <hi>Naman</hi> to the Prophet. A captiue woman, was the meanes of conuerting <hi>Iberia,</hi> now called <hi>Georgia. Eedeſius,</hi> &amp;<note place="margin">Ruffinus Eccle. Hiſt. lib. 1. cap. 9. 10. 1. Cor. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Frumentius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> two captiue youthes, were the meanes of bringing the goſpell into <hi>India.</hi> God makes the weake thinges of the worlde confound the mighty, and getteth himſelfe praiſe by the mouth of Babes and ſucklings. Be cheerfull then, and the Lord of all glory, glorifie his name by your happy ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the goſpell, to your commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his glory, that is Lord of all things, to whom be power and dominion for euer. <hi>Hallelu-iah.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11682:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
